<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Jeff Zych</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <id>http://jlzych.com/</id>
  <link href="http://jlzych.com/"/>
  <link href="http://jlzych.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2014-10-06T00:13:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jeff Zych</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>How Tina Fey’s “Lessons From Late Night” Apply to Product Design</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2014/10/05/how-tina-fey-s-lessons-from-late-night-apply-to-product-design/"/>
    <id>/2014/10/05/how-tina-fey-s-lessons-from-late-night-apply-to-product-design/</id>
    <published>2014-10-06T00:13:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-10-06T00:13:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In “&lt;a href="http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2011/03/14/lessons-from-late-night"&gt;Lessons From Late Night&lt;/a&gt;”, Tina Fey discusses the lessons she learned from Lorne Michaels while working at SNL. Turns out most of them are lessons I’ve learned in product design while working at &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com"&gt;Optimizely&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;“Producing is about discouraging creativity.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She goes on to say, “A TV show comprises many departments — costumes, props, talent, graphics, set dressing, transportation. Everyone in every department wants to show off his or her skills and contribute creatively to the show, which is a blessing.” But this creative energy must be harnessed and directed in a way that contributes positively to the sketch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applied to design, this basically means you need to say “no” a lot. Everyone’s full of ideas and will suggest things like, “Why don’t we just add a toggle so the user can choose their preference? More choice is good, right?” And then you need to explain that actually, users typically stick with the defaults, and don’t spend time configuring their software, and letting them toggle this option has all kinds of other product implications, so, no, sorry, lets try this other solution instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;“The show doesn’t go on because it’s ready; it goes on because it’s eleven-thirty.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a lesson in perfection. She elaborates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to try your hardest to be at the top of your game and improve every joke until the last possible second, but then you have to let it go.
You can’t be that kid standing at the top of the waterslide, overthinking it. You have to go down the chute. […] You have to let people see what you wrote. It will never be perfect, but perfect is overrated. Perfect is boring on live television.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just change a few words to “design” and “the web,” and this applies perfectly to product design. Designers can polish forever, but perfect is the enemy of done. But unlike SNL, Optimizely (and I imagine most startups) doesn’t often have hard 11:30 PM Saturday night deadlines, which means we have a tendency to let dates slip. I used to think that was great (“I can spend time polishing!”), but I’ve found that deadlines force you to make tough decisions in order to release product (such as cutting the scope of a feature). And that extra “polish” I think I’m adding is just me overthinking decisions I’ve already made and, oh, guess what, now that actual human beings are using it we need to cut or change those corners of the UI you’ve polished because actually they don’t matter at all now that it’s being used in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;“When hiring, mix Harvard nerds with Chicago improvisers and stir.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gist of this lesson is that diversity of thought is important when hiring. Having a variety of designers with different backgrounds and skills results in a better product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Optimizely, we have a mix of visual-designers-turned-UX-designers, designers formally trained in human–computer interaction and psychology (the Harvard nerds of the group, such as yours truly), and developers turned designers. We all push and learn from each other. “The Harvard guys check the logic and grammatical construction of every joke, and the improvisers teach them how to be human. It’s Spock and Kirk.” In our case, the HCI folks make sure designs are usable and don’t violate established interaction patterns, and the visual designers make sure we aren’t shipping a bunch of gray boxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;“Never cut to a closed door.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As applied to user experience design, this is a way of saying, “don’t leave the user at a dead end”. If users get to a screen where they can’t do anything, then you’ve lost them. Products often dump users in empty screens that have no content (we’ve made this mistake plenty at Optimizely), which lowers engagement and increases churn. Marketing pages can lack a call to action, leading to a high bounce rate. You should always provide clear next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;“Don’t hire anyone you wouldn’t want to run into in the hallway at three in the morning.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a way of saying hire people you enjoy working with. At Optimizely, culture is a huge part of the hiring process. Work is easier, more fun, and turns out better when you’re working with people you like and respect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing comedy and designing product don’t sound related, but there’s a lot of overlap in the creative process. As Tina’s lessons show, they each have a lot they can learn from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>1-year Retrospective</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2014/08/17/1-year-retrospective/"/>
    <id>/2014/08/17/1-year-retrospective/</id>
    <published>2014-08-18T04:13:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-08-18T04:13:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;August 2nd marked the 1-year anniversary of &lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/08/02/everyones-reading-this-increase-conversions-with-social-proof/"&gt;my first post&lt;/a&gt;, so it seems appropriate to do a quick retrospective of my first year blogging on my personal site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Writing Stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written 22 posts in that time, which is a rate of 1.83 per month. My (unstated) goal was 2 per month, so I wasn&amp;rsquo;t far off. My most prolific month is a tie between September 2013 and May 2014, in which I wrote 4 articles each. But in September I re-used some posts I had written previously for &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com"&gt;Optimizely&lt;/a&gt;, so May wins for more original content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, there were two months in which I didn&amp;rsquo;t write any articles: Dec 2013, and July 2014. In December I was in India, so that&amp;rsquo;s a pretty legitimate reason. July, however, has no good reason. It was generally a busy month, but I should have made time to write at least one post. And looking closer, just saying &amp;ldquo;July&amp;rdquo; makes it sound better than it actually was - I had a seven week stretch of no posts then!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My longest article was &lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2014/02/11/re-designing-optimizely-s-preview-tool/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Re-Designing Optimizely&amp;rsquo;s Preview Tool&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, clocking in at 4,158 words!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Site Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diving into Google Analytics, I&amp;rsquo;ve had 3,092 page views, 2,158 sessions, and 1,778 users. I seem to get a steady trickle of traffic every day, with a few occasional spikes in activity (which are caused by retweets, Facebook posts, or sending posts to all of Optimizely). All of which I find pretty surprising since I don&amp;rsquo;t write very regularly, and I don&amp;rsquo;t do much to actively seek readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Google Analytics stats for the past year" src="http://jlzych.com/images/2014-08-17-1-year-retrospective/ga.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So where do these visitors (i.e. you) come from? Google Analytics tells me that, even more surprisingly, the top two sources are organic search and direct, respectively. From looking through the search terms used to find me, they can be grouped into three categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My name: this is most likely people who are interviewing at Optimizely.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/08/15/performance-comparison-of-serving-fonts-through-typekit-vs-cloud-typography/"&gt;Cloud.typography and Typekit comparison&lt;/a&gt;: people are interested in a performance comparison of these two services. And in fact, I wrote this article precisely because I was searching for that information myself, but there weren&amp;rsquo;t any posts about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/09/30/framing-your-message-for-maximum-impact/"&gt;Framing messages&lt;/a&gt;: I wrote a post about the behavioral economics principle of framing, and how you can use it to generate A/B testing ideas. Apparently people want help writing headlines!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Top Posts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing to dig into Google Analytics, these are my three most popular posts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/10/08/extend-sass-s-awkward-stepchild/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Extend – SASS&amp;rsquo;s Awkward Stepchild&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, with 354 page views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2014/02/11/re-designing-optimizely-s-preview-tool/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Re-Designing Optimizely&amp;rsquo;s Preview Tool&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, with 306 page views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/08/15/performance-comparison-of-serving-fonts-through-typekit-vs-cloud-typography/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Performance comparison of serving fonts through Typekit vs Cloud.typography&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, with 302 page views.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re all pretty close in terms of traffic, but quite different in terms of content. So what does this tell me about what&amp;rsquo;s resonating with you, the reader, and what I should continue doing going forward? The main commonality is that all of those articles are original, in-depth content. In fact, this holds true past the top 10. My shorter posts that are responses to other people&amp;rsquo;s posts don&amp;rsquo;t receive as much mind share. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to think more about whether they&amp;rsquo;re worth doing at all anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;End&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall I&amp;rsquo;m pretty satisfied with those numbers, and the content I&amp;rsquo;ve been able to produce. Going forward I hope I can write more in-depth content, especially about the design process of my projects (which are my favorite to write). Here&amp;rsquo;s to the upcoming year!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>DRY isn't the One True Principle of CSS</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2014/08/10/dry-isn-t-the-one-true-principle-of-css/"/>
    <id>/2014/08/10/dry-isn-t-the-one-true-principle-of-css/</id>
    <published>2014-08-10T22:50:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-08-10T22:50:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://benfrain.com/"&gt;Ben Frain&lt;/a&gt; wrote a &lt;a href="http://benfrain.com/enduring-css-writing-style-sheets-rapidly-changing-long-lived-projects/"&gt;great article&lt;/a&gt; of recommendations for writing long-living CSS that&amp;rsquo;s authored by many people (e.g. CSS for a product). The whole thing is worth reading, but I especially agree with his argument against writing &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don&amp;#x27;t_repeat_yourself"&gt;DRY&lt;/a&gt; (Don&amp;rsquo;t Repeat Yourself) code at the expense of maintainability. He says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a concrete example; being able to delete an entire Sass partial (say 9KB) in six months time with impunity (in that I know what will and won’t be affected by the removal) is far more valuable to me than a 1KB saving enjoyed because I re-used or extended some vague abstracted styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, by abstracting styles as much as possible and maximizing re-use, you&amp;rsquo;re creating an invisible web of dependencies. If you ever want to change or remove styles, you will cause a ripple effect throughout your site. Tasks that should have been 30 or 60 minutes balloon into multi-hour endeavors. As Ben says, being able to delete (or modify) with impunity is far more valuable than the small savings you get by abstracting your code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made this mistake many times in my career, and it took me a long time to distinguish between good and bad code reuse. The trick I use is to ask, &amp;ldquo;If I were to later change the style of this component, would I want the others that depend on it to be updated, too?&amp;rdquo; More often than not, the answer is no, and the styles should be written separately. It took some time for me to be comfortable having duplicate CSS in order to increase maintainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of thinking about this is to figure out why two components look the same. If it&amp;rsquo;s because one is a modification of a base module (e.g. a small version of a button), it&amp;rsquo;s a good candidate for code reuse. If not (e.g. a tab that looks similar to a button, but behaves differently), then you&amp;rsquo;re just setting yourself up for a maintainability nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As beneficial as DRY code is, it isn&amp;rsquo;t the One True Principle of CSS. At best, it saves some time and bytes, but at worst, it&amp;rsquo;s a hindrance to CSS maintainability.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Design Process of Optimizely's Sample Size Calculator</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2014/06/18/design-process-of-optimizely-s-sample-size-calculator/"/>
    <id>/2014/06/18/design-process-of-optimizely-s-sample-size-calculator/</id>
    <published>2014-06-18T15:24:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-06-18T15:24:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Optimizely just released a &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com/resources/sample-size-calculator"&gt;sample size calculator&lt;/a&gt;, which tells people how many visitors they need for an A/B test to get results. This page began as a hack week project, which produced a functioning page, but needed some design love before being ready for primetime. So my coworker &lt;a href="http://jonsaquing.com/"&gt;Jon&lt;/a&gt; (a &lt;a href="http://www.jobscore.com/jobs2/optimizely/communication-designer/cEhJpKd7qr45_4iGakhP3Q?ref=rss&amp;amp;sid=68"&gt;communication designer&lt;/a&gt; at Optimizely) and I teamed up to push this page over the finish line. In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to explain the design decisions we made along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Finished sample size calculator" src="http://jlzych.com/images/2014-06-18-design-process-of-optimizely-s-sample-size-calculator/calculator-done.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The finished sample size calculator&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;We Started with a Functioning Prototype&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The page started as an &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com"&gt;Optimizely&lt;/a&gt; hack week project that functioned correctly, but suffered from a confusing layout that didn&amp;rsquo;t guide people through the calculation. After brainstorming some ideas, we decided the calculator’s layout should follow the form of basic math taught in primary school. You start at the top, write down each of the inputs in a column, and calculate the answer at the bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Original sample size calculator prototype" src="http://jlzych.com/images/2014-06-18-design-process-of-optimizely-s-sample-size-calculator/calculator-proto.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The original sample size calculator prototype&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made sense conceptually, but put the most important piece of data (the number of visitors needed) at the bottom of the page. Conventional wisdom and design theory would say our information hierarchy is backwards, and users may not even see this content. It also meant the answer is below the fold, which could increase the bounce rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of these fears make sense when viewing the page through the lens of static content. But this page is interactive, and requires input from the user to produce a meaningful answer to how many visitors are needed for an &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com/ab-testing"&gt;A/B test&lt;/a&gt;. Lining up the inputs in a vertical column, and placing the answer at the bottom, encourages people to look at each piece of data going into the calculation, and enter appropriate values before getting an answer. The risk of visitors bouncing, or not seeing the answer, is minimal. Although this is counter to best practices, we felt our reasons for breaking the rules were sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, we did our due diligence and sketched a few variations that shuffled around the inputs (e.g. horizontal; multi-column) and the sample size per variation (e.g. top; sides). None of these alternates felt right, and having the final answer at the bottom made the most sense for the reasons described above. But sketching out other ideas made us confident in our original design decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Power User Inputs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After deciding on the basic layout of the page, we tackled the statistical power and significance inputs. We knew from discussions with our statisticians that mathematically speaking these were important variables in the calculation, but they don&amp;rsquo;t need to be changed by most people. The primary user of this page just wants to know how many visitors they&amp;rsquo;ll need to run through an A/B test, for whom the mathematical details of these variables are unimportant. However, the values should still be clear to all users, and editable for power users who understand their effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve this challenge, we decided to display the value in plain text, but hide the controls behind an &amp;ldquo;Edit&amp;rdquo; button. Clicking the button reveals a slider to change the input. We agreed that this solution gave enough friction to deter most users from playing around with these values, but it&amp;rsquo;s not so burdensome as to frustrate an expert user who wants to change it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Removing the &amp;ldquo;Calculate&amp;rdquo; Button&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original version of the page didn&amp;rsquo;t spit out the number of visitors until the &amp;ldquo;Calculate&amp;rdquo; button was clicked. But once I started using the page and personally experienced the annoyance of having to click this button every time I changed the values, it was clear the whole process would be a lot smoother if the answer updated automatically anytime an input changed. This makes the page much more fluid to use, and encourages people to play with each variable to see how it affects the number of visitors their test needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a design decision that only became clear to me from using a working implementation. In a static mock, a button will look fine and come across as an adequate user experience. But it&amp;rsquo;s hard to assess the user experience unless you can actually &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt; a working implementation. Once I re-implemented the page, it was clear auto-updating the answer was a superior experience. But without actually trying each version, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been confident in that decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project was a fun cross-collaboration between product and communication design at Optimizely. I focused on the interactions and implementation, while Jon focused on the visual design, but we sat side-by-side and talked through each decision together, sketching and pushing each other along the way. Ultimately, the finished product landed in a better place from this collaboration. It was a fun little side project that we hope adds value to the customer experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I, Too, Only Work On Unshiny Products</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2014/05/25/i-too-only-work-on-unshiny-products/"/>
    <id>/2014/05/25/i-too-only-work-on-unshiny-products/</id>
    <published>2014-05-25T18:55:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-05-25T18:55:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/design-founders/847701785dae"&gt;Jeff Domke&amp;rsquo;s article&lt;/a&gt; about working on &amp;ldquo;unshiny&amp;rdquo; products sums up my view of my own work at &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com"&gt;Optimizely&lt;/a&gt;. The crux of his argument is that many designers are drawn to working on &amp;ldquo;shiny&amp;rdquo; products — products that are pretty and lauded in the design community — but &amp;ldquo;unshiny&amp;rdquo; products are a lot more interesting to work on. They&amp;rsquo;re often solving difficult problems, and have more room for you to make an impact. You&amp;rsquo;re working to make the product reach its potential. Shiny products, on the other hand, have reached that potential, and you are less able to make your mark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimizely sits right in the sweet spot. We aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;shiny&amp;rdquo; (compared to sexy products like Square and Medium, we have a long way to go); nor are we &amp;ldquo;unshiny&amp;rdquo; (our customers describe us as well-designed and easy-to-use). Rather, we land more in the middle — we have a solid user experience that has a lot of room for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re also solving really hairy, complex problems. Apps that get mounds of praise tend to solve relatively simple problems (such as to-do list apps). It&amp;rsquo;s much more interesting to work on a problem space that is unexplored and is full of murky, vague, conflicting goals that must be untangled. And once you&amp;rsquo;ve made sense of the mess, you know you&amp;rsquo;ve enabled someone to do their job better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s the most exciting part of working at Optimizely — making the product fulfill its potential, and solving tough problems that impact businesses&amp;#39; bottom lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Want to come work on hard problems with me at Optimizely? Check out our &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com/jobs"&gt;jobs&lt;/a&gt;, or reach out &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jlzych"&gt;@jlzych&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Being a Generalist</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2014/05/19/on-being-a-generalist/"/>
    <id>/2014/05/19/on-being-a-generalist/</id>
    <published>2014-05-20T04:02:00Z</published>
    <updated>2014-05-20T04:02:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently read &lt;a href="http://frankchimero.com/intros/quilt/"&gt;Frank Chimero&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s excellent article, &lt;a href="http://frankchimero.com/talks/designing-in-the-borderlands/transcript/"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Designing in the Borderlands&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. The gist of it is that we (designers, and the larger tech community) have constructed walls between various disciplines that we see as opposites, such as print vs. digital, text vs. image, and so on. However, the most interesting design happens in the borderlands, where these different media connect. He cites examples that combine physical and digital media, but the most interesting bit for me was his thoughts on roles that span disciplines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a long time, I perceived my practice’s sprawl as a defect—evidence of an itchy mind or a fear of commitment—but I am starting to learn that a disadvantage can turn into an advantage with a change of venue. The ability to cross borders is an asset. Who else could go from group to group and be welcomed? The pattern happens over and over: if you’re not a part of any group, you can move amongst them all by tip-toeing across the lines that connect them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have felt this way many times throughout my career (especially that &amp;ldquo;fear of commitment&amp;rdquo; part). I have long felt like a generalist who works in both design and engineering, and I label myself to help people understand what I do (not to mention the necessity of a title). But I&amp;rsquo;ve never cleanly fit into any discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line was further blurred by my graduate degree from UC Berkeley&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://ischool.berkeley.edu"&gt;School of Information&lt;/a&gt;. The program brings together folks with diverse backgrounds, and produces &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-shaped_skills"&gt;T-shaped people&lt;/a&gt; who can think across disciplines and understand the broader context of their work, whether it be in engineering, design, policy &amp;amp; law, sociology, or dozens of other fields in which our alumni call home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These borderlands are the best place for a designer like me, and maybe like you, because the borderlands are where things connect. If you’re in the borderlands, your different tongues, your scattered thoughts, your lack of identification with a group, and all the things that used to be thought of as drawbacks in a specialist enclave become the hardened armor of a shrewd generalist in the borderlands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couldn&amp;rsquo;t have said it any better. Being able to move between groups and think across disciplines is more of an advantage than a disadvantage.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
