<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Jeff Zych</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <id>http://jlzych.com/</id>
  <link href="http://jlzych.com/"/>
  <link href="http://jlzych.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2020-03-30T00:09:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jeff Zych</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Site Redesign IV: Color, Layout, &amp; Logo</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2020/03/29/site-redesign-iv-color-layout-logo/"/>
    <id>/2020/03/29/site-redesign-iv-color-layout-logo/</id>
    <published>2020-03-30T00:09:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-03-30T00:09:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;While I was exploring the &lt;a href="/2020/03/15/site-redesign-iii-typography/"&gt;world of typography&lt;/a&gt; to match my &lt;a href="/2020/01/27/site-redesign-i-the-guiding-concept/"&gt;guiding concept&lt;/a&gt;, I was also exploring ideas for the color, layout, and logo (some of which you saw in the &lt;a href="/2020/03/15/site-redesign-iii-typography/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;). I explored all 3 of these together because they were all interrelated. The placement of the logo and navigation dictated their color and style, so I was changing each variable simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My starting point was summer and beach — blue skies and water, warm sun, yellow sand, and so on. These ended up being both too cool-toned, and like I was getting fried on the beach under the bright mid-day sun. They were too literal. But hey, you have to start somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/1-blues.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of exploring blue skies and water, warm sun, and yellow sand." src="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/1-blues.png?1585533231" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Exploring blue skies and water, warm sun, and yellow sand.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I switched to a warmer palette, and using fat bands of solid color that I pulled from my mood board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/2-oranges.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of warmer palettes with fat bands of color." src="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/2-oranges.png?1585533231" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Warmer palettes with fat bands of color.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also tried out a &amp;ldquo;watercolored&amp;rdquo; (it was done in Procreate) header, and while the colors were nice, the aesthetic felt too artistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/3-watercolors.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of watercolor header." src="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/3-watercolors.png?1585533231" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Watercolor header.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While none of these were working as is, the colors were moving in the right direction. These explorations also helped me refine the aesthetic towards a 60s/70s California summer vibe (as described in the &lt;a href="/2020/02/10/site-redesign-ii-inspiration/"&gt;inspiration post&lt;/a&gt;). That pushed me to notice sunsets more. Specifically the time right when the sun is setting and the sky is a warm blue and the horizon is orange. That palette had just the right tones. The blues of my previous exploration were too bright and cool-toned, but this blue felt warm and comforting. And the orange paired with it perfectly (you can&amp;rsquo;t go wrong taking inspiration from nature, y&amp;#39;all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/sunset-photos.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Pictures of sunsets that inspired me" src="/images/2020-redesign/sunset-photos.png?1581401423" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pictures of sunsets that inspired me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not too long after this (or maybe before, the timeline is impossible to keep track of) I saw the site design of &lt;a href="https://iheanyi.com/"&gt;Iheanyi Ekechukwu&lt;/a&gt; via &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julesforrest/status/1163185120456531968"&gt;Jules Forrest&amp;rsquo;s tweet&lt;/a&gt;. I combined his site layout with my sunset-inspired gradient, and violà! I had the basic frame for my site. I gave the content a warm, off-white background, and made the text a warm brown-ish orange, and the main content&amp;rsquo;s style snapped into place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="navigation-amp-logo"&gt;Navigation &amp;amp; Logo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I was heavily influenced by &lt;a href="https://iheanyi.com/"&gt;Iheanyi Ekechukwu&amp;rsquo;s site&lt;/a&gt;, my navigation and logo were different from his, so I still needed to figure out where to place them, and how to style them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried them both inside and outside the main content area, in various blues, oranges, whites, and blacks. I didn&amp;rsquo;t fall in love with any option, and eventually settled on a temporary location of the navigation being dark blue and sitting above the main content while I tried out various type options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/5-nav-logo.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of logo and navigation above content." src="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/5-nav-logo.png?1585533231" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Logo and navigation above content.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also struggling with the JZ monogram. The hand drawn warmth of it still fit with the site&amp;rsquo;s new guiding light, but where do I put it? How do I style it? This took awhile to nail down. Like the navigation, I settled on the logo sitting above the content area in a light orange while I played with type (see image above), but that option never felt right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I set the type, I revisited these temporary decisions. I hit reset and started over with the design of Iheanyi Ekechuku&amp;rsquo;s site. The thinner outside gradient, combined with everything inside the white content area, felt cleaner, lighter, and put the emphasis on the content while having just enough color to make the site visually interesting and pull your eyes down the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the navigation dark blue so it would be of secondary importance to the content, and placed it in the top left corner, and that felt about right. At the last minute I switched it to a lighter brown color because I decided the blue was actually calling too much attention to itself. I must have done this in code because I couldn&amp;rsquo;t find it in Figma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I was left with the logo, and let me tell you — this was a struggle. I converged on its placement pretty quickly (left side of the content, top-aligned with it), but couldn&amp;rsquo;t find any color or style that fit with the guiding concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I churned out dozens of variations, of which a good 20 or so survived in Figma. I tried strokes, shadows, different colors and backgrounds, and more. I tried a bunch of tricks I learned from doing hand lettering, and was confident I had a style somewhere in my tool belt that would work. Alas, nothing stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/6-monograms1.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of monogram variations." src="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/6-monograms1.png?1585533231" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A subset of monogram variations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eventually hit a wall, so I sought out more inspiration. I scoured &lt;a href="https://www.fontsinuse.com"&gt;Fonts in Use&lt;/a&gt; posts, Google image searched for retro posters, and browsed 60s/70s lettering. I eventually found a hand-lettered style of big, chunky type that was duplicated and offset many times in different colors (inspiration that I apparently never saved anywhere).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried that out and could tell I was in the right ballpark (see image below). I played around with the offest colors, sizes, and directions until landing on what you see today (see them all in my &lt;a href="https://www.figma.com/c/file/808494599049531462/jlzych.com-site-explorations-2019"&gt;Figma Community file&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/7-monograms2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of monogram explorations in the right ballpark." src="/images/2020-redesign/color-layout/7-monograms2.png?1585533231" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Monogram explorations in the right ballpark.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy with the final result, although I find the colors a little too bright (especially in contexts off the site, like the favicon and Twitter), so I need to desaturate it and tweak the colors a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing I did, mostly in code, was the link style. I knew I wanted a link style that didn&amp;rsquo;t call too much attention to itself, but at the same time they were an opportunity to give the text some visual flair. I can&amp;rsquo;t remember exactly what I tried, but when I saw the bright blue underline style, I knew that was it. I decided to make the underline &amp;ldquo;grow&amp;rdquo; on hover as a nice way to do something different and surprise readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that, my friends, sums up my journey of how I redesigned this site. It took multiple years of off-and-on bursts of activity going back all the way to when I started adding hand lettering to the site, but the end result is a massive leap forward. I will continue tweaking it, but I&amp;rsquo;m confident the core aesthetic will serve me for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.figma.com/c/file/808494599049531462/jlzych.com-site-explorations-2019"&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you want to see all the iterations and gory detail of how I got to the site as you see it today, I published my work on Figma Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Site Redesign III: Typography</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2020/03/15/site-redesign-iii-typography/"/>
    <id>/2020/03/15/site-redesign-iii-typography/</id>
    <published>2020-03-15T23:43:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-03-15T23:43:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before I started &lt;a href="/2020/02/10/site-redesign-ii-inspiration/"&gt;moodboarding&lt;/a&gt;, or even found my &lt;a href="/2020/01/27/site-redesign-i-the-guiding-concept/"&gt;guiding concept&lt;/a&gt; (as documented in those previous two posts), I read &lt;a href="https://www.abramsbooks.com/product/designers-dictionary-of-type_9781419737183/"&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Designer&amp;rsquo;s Dictionary of Type&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and realized the typography on my site was not particularly warm or human. The fonts I had at the time were Myriad Black for headlines and interface copy (e.g. navigation), and Minion for body copy. (Before that I used Minion everywhere — even more boring). These fonts paired nicely together, and are well-made, but they&amp;rsquo;re too bland, corporate, and impersonal for a personal website. Once again, these decisions were made out of a desire to &amp;ldquo;not look bad.&amp;rdquo; They certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like &lt;em&gt;me&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Designer&amp;rsquo;s Dictionary of Type&lt;/em&gt;, mixed with a couple years of &lt;a href="/scribbles"&gt;hand lettering&lt;/a&gt;, helped me see how all the small details and idiosyncracies of a typeface gave it personality. Before making a serious attempt to give my site a facelift (as documented here), I knew I wanted more human typography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first attempt, before I even had my guiding concept, was swapping Myriad for Gill Sans. Gill is similar to Myriad, but has unique letterforms for a sans, like the triangle-topped &amp;ldquo;t&amp;rdquo;. I tried it on, probably in code since I didn&amp;rsquo;t find it in Figma, and immediately discarded it. It looked fine, but overall my site still felt the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started keeping an eye out for more fonts to try and subscribed to &lt;a href="https://fontsinuse.com/"&gt;Fonts in Use&lt;/a&gt; to give me a steady stream of font inspiration. During this time I found my guiding concept and started gathering inspiration. I was being drawn to warm, friendly typefaces from the 60s and 70s, like Cooper Black. This melded with the &amp;ldquo;summer&amp;rdquo; guiding light, and I realized this style of type would be a great way to express warmth and summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first tried on Cooper for size, since it&amp;rsquo;s the quintessential 70s font, and it (unsurprisingly) didn&amp;rsquo;t fit at all (screenshots below, which show various ideas I was workshopping). It felt too much like a novelty. Too flower power 🌸✌️☮︎ Also, Garfield. But I had to try it to be sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/typography/1-cooper.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of Cooper Black as my headline font." src="/images/2020-redesign/typography/1-cooper.png?1584336919" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Cooper Black as the headline font. What a goofball.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started casting about for another font in the spirit of Cooper. A font that has the round, soft serifs of Cooper, but is a little more serious. I scoured Adobe Fonts, Google Fonts, &lt;a href="https://www.typewolf.com/"&gt;Typewolf&lt;/a&gt;, and more, but didn&amp;rsquo;t find anything worth trying. I searched for &amp;ldquo;rounded serifs,&amp;rdquo; and browsed 60s and 70s type lists, all to no avail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After cooling my search for a few months, Mackinac came to me via a &lt;a href="https://www.niceverynice.com/stories/font-pairings"&gt;Nice Very Nice font pairings article&lt;/a&gt; (which came to me from Sidebar). They featured Mackinac as used on &lt;a href="https://patternbrands.com/"&gt;Pattern Brands&amp;rsquo; site&lt;/a&gt;. Seeing it used there, it felt warm and friendly and inviting. I was excited to try it on, but when I did&amp;hellip; flop. It was a little &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; straight-laced. The edges of the serif were a bit too pointy. A little more rigid. It just wasn&amp;rsquo;t as warm and inviting on my site as I was hoping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/typography/2-mackinac-pattern.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of Mackinac as the headline font for Pattern Brands." src="/images/2020-redesign/typography/2-mackinac-pattern.jpeg?1584336920" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Mackinac as the headline font for Pattern Brands.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was back to square one, but this time not for long. &lt;a href="https://www.myfonts.com/fonts/itc/souvenir/"&gt;Souvenir&lt;/a&gt; came across my desk, I&amp;rsquo;m guessing via one of &lt;a href="https://fontsinuse.com/uses/28652/le-jardin-soupire"&gt;these&lt;/a&gt; two &lt;a href="https://fontsinuse.com/uses/28687/emmanuelle-1974-u-s-movie-posters"&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; on Fonts in Use. That also led me to &lt;a href="https://fonts.adobe.com/fonts/gastromond"&gt;Gastromond&lt;/a&gt;, probably by searching for similar typefaces (or maybe I was just browsing Adobe Fonts? Who knows).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/typography/3-souvenir-gastromond.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of Souvenir and Gastromond type specimens." src="/images/2020-redesign/typography/3-souvenir-gastromond.png?1584336919" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Souvenir on top, Gastromond on the bottom.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Souvenir, I loved the warmth and friendliness that came from its soft edges and nice wide, round letterforms. The &amp;ldquo;e&amp;rdquo; has a great laid back vibe that I love. The lowercase &amp;ldquo;v&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;y&amp;rdquo;, uppercase &amp;ldquo;A&amp;rdquo;, and a few other letters have a little bit of bowing to them that make them feel relaxed and happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Gastromond, its off-axis counterforms make it feel like it&amp;rsquo;s leaning back and relaxed. I also loved the contrast between the thick and thin strokes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried them both on, and Souvenir was the clear winner. It was warm, friendly, a little funky and retro, all without feeling goofy or like a novelty font. It retained just enough seriousness to not undermine the generally serious tone of my writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gastromond was a little too pointy, and not as warm as I was hoping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/typography/4-gastro-souvenir.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of Gastromond and Souvenir on an early exploration of my site." src="/images/2020-redesign/typography/4-gastro-souvenir.png?1584336919" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Headlines set as Gastromond on the left, and Souvenir on the right, using an early design exploration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went with Souvenir Bold to really lean into its personality. It borders on chunky at times, but the Medium weight felt too timid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My only complaint about Souvenir is the kerning is sometimes off. At times letters run into each other (like around the lowercase &amp;ldquo;i&amp;quot;s), and other times my eyes trip over the space between letters (like between &amp;quot;v&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;o&amp;rdquo;). The kerning of the numbers is also too wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="body-copy"&gt;Body Copy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having finally found a headline font, I was on to the next challenge: body copy. The headline took a long time to find, but I was at least chasing a muse, and knew it when I saw it. But I had no idea what to do with the body copy. What pairs with a warm 70s serif? Another serif? A sans-serif? Blackletter? Souvenir is often used in signs, storefronts, posters, and record covers — not editorials. I had no idea where to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Souvenir is a serif, my first move was to pair it with a sans serif. Classic pairing. But I was never too keen on this idea because my site is a blog, and it&amp;rsquo;s mostly longform content, so I prefer serifs for their ease of reading and the editorial tone they imbue the text with. I want the content to be taken seriously, so the typeface should reflect that, but still have some warmth to it to match the headline font. It shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be overly literary or stuffy or newspaper-y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first tried some wider sans, including Proxima Nova and Open Sans. But they were still sans, so the reading experience wasn&amp;rsquo;t great, and overall they just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel right. Even so, Open Sans wasn&amp;rsquo;t awful, so I kept it in my back pocket for awhile and used it in Figma while trying out different layouts and colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/typography/5-opensans-proxima.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of body copy set in Open Sans and Proxima Nova." src="/images/2020-redesign/typography/5-opensans-proxima.png?1584336919" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Body copy set in Open Sans on the left, Proxima Nova on the right, in another early exploration.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I moved on to some classic serifs, like Times New Roman and Caslon and Georgia, but they felt too stuffy. I liked Georgia the best so far, and it was my leading choice for quite a while. It also had the advantage of being free and preinstalled on everyone&amp;rsquo;s devices, thus fast to load.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/typography/6-georgia-caslon.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of body copy set as Georgia and Caslon." src="/images/2020-redesign/typography/6-georgia-caslon.png?1584336919" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Body copy set as Georgia on the left, Caslon on the right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I liked Georgia and Open Sans, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; them the way I loved Souvenir. I knew I had to keep pushing to find something better. I asked myself, what is it that&amp;rsquo;s working about those fonts? The characteristics that gelled with Souvenir were their wide, round, open letterforms, and tall x-heights. Open Sans also had a softness about it that came from a lack of serifs. Nothing that could poke your eye out. These characteristics paired well with Souvenir.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This led me to search for a serif that was round, open, tall x-height, but friendlier and softer and a little lighter than Georgia. Once again, I trawled Adobe Fonts, Google Fonts, Fonts in Use, Typewolf, and more. Searching for a font to meet those requirements was tough — there weren&amp;rsquo;t filters for the specific attributes I was looking for. I just browsed long lists of serifs for body copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Adobe Fonts I eventually came across &lt;a href="https://fonts.adobe.com/fonts/mrs-eaves-xl"&gt;Mrs Eaves XL&lt;/a&gt;, which is a modern revival of the classic Mrs Eaves, but made for setting &amp;ldquo;long readerly texts.&amp;rdquo; It has round, open letter forms, was easy to read at body copy sizes, and was warmer, more human, and lighter than Georgia. It also has &lt;em&gt;beautiful italics&lt;/em&gt; (especially the &amp;ldquo;w&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;v&amp;rdquo;). I tried it out in Figma and 🙌.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="interface-text"&gt;Interface text&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there was the question of what to do with interface copy. Specifically, the navigation and links to Twitter after each post. You may remember from the beginning of this post (which was ages ago in real-time), I tried out Gill Sans. I also tried Gill Sans Black, which is basically its own distinct typeface, and super unique. Neither worked as headlines, but the fun quirkiness of Gill Sans Black stayed with me. On a lark, I ended up setting the navigation links to that in Figma while messing around with other fonts, layouts, and colors, with the assumption that I would change it later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out, I never had any other serious contenders. I tried out some other sans serif options, like Verdana, Myriad, and regular Gill Sans, but none of them were doing it for me. After seeing Gill Sans Black in there over and over again it grew on me. When I saw it set alongside Souvenir and Mrs Eaves XL, it worked in a funky, unexplainable way. Certainly not a conventional choice, but I loved how opinionated its personality was, and how that makes it stand out so distinctly from the rest of the type on the site. It clearly signals to visitors that this text is different from everything else you&amp;rsquo;ve been looking at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="type-scale"&gt;Type Scale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 6 months later, I finally had my fonts. The final piece of the puzzle was defining my type scale. I&amp;rsquo;m not particularly rigorous about this process. No fancy math or ratios to calculate my type sizes, leading, and margins. Instead, I started with some rough sizing in Figma, and then iterated in code so I could make adjustments with real content until it looked right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My starting point from Figma was too large, so I cut down my headlines across the board. I started with the H4, which is the deepest I go, setting it just large enough to stand out from the copy (easy to do since the typefaces are so different). Then I set the H1 large and in charge to communicate its importance, and lean into its personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For H2 and H3, I chose some sizes between H1 and H4. These are always the toughest for me to set because they&amp;rsquo;re the in the middle. Is it too big? Too small? I dunno 🤷‍♂️ I try to make sure they&amp;rsquo;re just different enough to be distinct, that when I scroll through the page they set pieces of text apart from each other, when squinting they still stand out as headlines, and that when all 4 are next to each other they have a clear hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also looked at the spacing between headlines and paragraphs, cutting down the margins between some elements so that the page had a smooth rhythm while scrolling. In other words, no gaps for your eyes to trip over. While going through this process, Frank Chimero &lt;a href="https://frankchimero.com/blog/2020/gardening-vs-architecture/"&gt;blogged about his process for this&lt;/a&gt;, which helped me get to my final design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="game-set-match"&gt;Game, Set, Match.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, the better part of a year later, my typography was set. You can check out a fraction of my explorations in the screenshot below, or check out my &lt;a href="https://www.figma.com/c/file/808494599049531462/jlzych.com-site-explorations-2019"&gt;published Figma file&lt;/a&gt; to browse everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/typography/7-explorations.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of a bunch of type explorations in Figma" src="/images/2020-redesign/typography/7-explorations.png?1584336919" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A fraction of my type explorations (and visual design ideas) in Figma.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t an easy process, and the road was far from straight, but in the end I&amp;rsquo;m really happy with how it turned out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up is the site layout and color palette.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Site Redesign II: Inspiration</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2020/02/10/site-redesign-ii-inspiration/"/>
    <id>/2020/02/10/site-redesign-ii-inspiration/</id>
    <published>2020-02-11T05:53:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-02-11T05:53:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Having found my guiding concept in my &lt;a href="/2020/01/27/site-redesign-i-the-guiding-concept/"&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; (tl;dr is it should feel like me, but on the internet, as expressed through SoCal summer vibes), I started gathering inspiration for how to translate that into colors, fonts, and an overall site design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right off the bat I had a couple of shirts and posters in mind that had the exact vibe I wanted. They said &amp;ldquo;California&amp;rdquo; (literally and figuratively), warmth, and summer to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/inspo-1.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Shirts and posters that immediately inspired me" src="/images/2020-redesign/inspo-1.png?1581401423" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Shirts and posters that immediately inspired me. I own the shirts in the top left.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, I kept my eyes peeled while browsing Instagram, reading my daily dose of design blogs, and experiencing the world. I screenshotted my favorites and photographed sunsets (specifically the time right when the sun is getting at or below the horizon, which has beautiful oranges, yellows, and a warm blue sky).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/sunset-photos.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Pictures of sunsets that inspired me" src="/images/2020-redesign/sunset-photos.png?1581401423" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Pictures of sunsets that inspired me&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the months (I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in a hurry, and this work was mostly passive), I got pulled towards 60s/70s styles, which often have a warm color palette, rounded serifs (like Cooper), and repeating lines and shapes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/60s-70s.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="60s and 70s graphics I was diggin" src="/images/2020-redesign/60s-70s.png?1581401423" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;60s and 70s graphics I was diggin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the site itself, I was inspired by a &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/julesforrest/status/1163185120456531968"&gt;tweet I saw from Jules Forrest&lt;/a&gt; praising the site design of &lt;a href="https://iheanyi.com/"&gt;Iheanyi Ekechukwu&lt;/a&gt;. I loved the gradient border/background, and the otherwise simple layout with its focus on the content. An image immediately snapped into my head of this layout and gradient, but with my 60s/70s summer color palette.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/iheanyi.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of Iheanyi's website" src="/images/2020-redesign/iheanyi.jpeg?1581401424" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Screenshot of Iheanyi&amp;rsquo;s website that Jules posted&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This gave me enough direction to start choosing typography and a color palette for the site, which I&amp;rsquo;ll describe in my next posts. In the meantime, check out my &lt;a href="https://www.figma.com/c/file/808494599049531462/jlzych.com-site-explorations-2019"&gt;Figma file that I published&lt;/a&gt; on their community page (which contains spoilers for the actual site design).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Site Redesign I: The Guiding Concept</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2020/01/27/site-redesign-i-the-guiding-concept/"/>
    <id>/2020/01/27/site-redesign-i-the-guiding-concept/</id>
    <published>2020-01-28T06:22:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-28T06:22:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As some of you may have noticed, I (semi-)recently gave my site a visual overhaul. It&amp;rsquo;s far more opinionated than before, so I want to document my decision making process over the next couple of posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/before-after.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of my site before and after the redesign" src="/images/2020-redesign/before-after.png?1581401423" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Before (left): a dull gray background. Minion typeface throughout. After (right): much warmer. More engaging. More personality.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up is the concept that drove the visual design of the site. The concept took a long time to come into focus, but is the most important (and hardest) part of the redesign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I transitioned my site from a portfolio to a blog (circa 2012, after graudating from grad school), there was no concept behind it. I just wanted a site that &amp;ldquo;didn&amp;rsquo;t look bad&amp;rdquo; and was easy to read (it was a &lt;em&gt;blog&lt;/em&gt;, remember?). That meant safe, overused typeface (Minion). Minimal color. No ornamentation. Nothing flashy or special at all, really. Just text on a page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;JZ&lt;/em&gt; monogram was just the letters set in a nice font, cut out of a box. I designed it like that because I thought it looked cool. The image came to me one day, so I whipped it up in Illustrator. I chose the blue-kissed green because it looked nice and was neither flashy nor boring. Not exactly the strongest reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ended up with a site that looked fine, and avoided making mistakes, but that was it. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t special or unique or interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s how my site was for many years. It did its job. But as the site kept evolving, I wanted the design to be more opinionated and memorable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s when I started looking for a stronger point of view to express. A feeling to evoke. A guiding concept to build around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My starting point was just to make my site feel more personal. It&amp;rsquo;s my site. A blog. Not a corporate site. Not a product page. Not a publication. So I should express myself more. That led me to swap my knocked-out JZ with a hand-lettered monogram a couple of years back. I also added a better photo and a hand-lettered &amp;ldquo;Hello!&amp;rdquo; on my about page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/images/2020-redesign/about-before-after.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="Screenshot of my about page before and after the redesign" src="/images/2020-redesign/about-before-after.png?1581401423" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Before (left 2): I don&amp;rsquo;t have a screenshot of the original about page, but the leftmost image is an unstyled version of the page from the Wayback Machine, and isn&amp;rsquo;t far off from how it looked. The middle one is a revamped page from some number of years ago. After (right): how it looks at the time of this post. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t fully live up to the new concept, but is the best yet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these all undoubtedly improved my site, the concept wasn&amp;rsquo;t strong enough to stand on its own two legs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pushed myself to go deeper. &amp;ldquo;What does more personal mean? What makes a website &amp;lsquo;personal&amp;rsquo; anyway?&amp;rdquo; I didn&amp;rsquo;t have answers, but they were good provocations to keep in the back of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I let those questions marinate (for more than a year, probably — it&amp;rsquo;s hard to remember, exactly), I read &lt;em&gt;Conversational Design&lt;/em&gt; by Erika Hall, who recommends thinking of a website (or app, or any touchpoint) as a person as a way to create a memorable design (which I also read about many years ago in &lt;em&gt;Well Designed&lt;/em&gt; by Jon Kolko and forgot about). How would that person talk? Act? Dress?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s when all these disparate ideas — making my site &amp;ldquo;more personal;&amp;rdquo; the website as extension of self; touchpoints as people — fused into one: my site should be an extension of me! When people interact with my site, it should feel like interacting with me IRL (that&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;in real life&lt;/em&gt; for the older crowd).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept immediately connected with me. There was just one problem: how do I do that? What does it mean to translate myself into a digital medium? How does a website &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo; like me? What feelings do people get when they see me, or think of me? How would my friends describe me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It got very existential very quickly. 😳 Who am I? What defines me? Shorts? T-shirts? Owls? Bravo reality TV?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure how to answer. And once again, I let this idea marinate in the back of my brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After many months (at least), I was in the kitchen at work wearing my customary shorts and owl t-shirt, when my coworker reacted with surprise at my outfit (it was winter), and said, &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s like you always bring summer with you wherever you go!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BOOM! 💥 That was the underlying concept I was looking for! Summer, warm, friendly, beach-y, So Cal vibes. Those were feelings I could evoke on the screen with visual design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next up, I&amp;rsquo;ll write about how I turned those into the color and font choices you&amp;rsquo;re seeing now (unless you&amp;rsquo;re from the future).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Books Read 2019</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2020/01/22/books-read-2019/"/>
    <id>/2020/01/22/books-read-2019/</id>
    <published>2020-01-23T05:49:00Z</published>
    <updated>2020-01-23T05:49:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In 2019 I read 30 books, which is pretty good considering some were huge like &lt;em&gt;The System of the World&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Power Broker&lt;/em&gt;. Also, I got married 🤵👰, and it turns out planning takes a ton of time. Other books, though, were glorified picture books, like &lt;em&gt;Palette Perfect&lt;/em&gt;, so I guess it all evens out. It&amp;rsquo;s also 7 more books than I &lt;a href="/2019/01/03/books-read-2018/"&gt;read last year&lt;/a&gt;, and more than double &lt;a href="/2017/12/31/books-read-in-2017/"&gt;2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="favorite-non-fiction"&gt;Favorite Non-fiction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Power Broker&lt;/em&gt; by Robert Caro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hands down the best non-fiction book I&amp;rsquo;ve read. It took me a long time to work up the courage to start it since it&amp;rsquo;s huge, but boy was it worth it. I was worried it would be dry since it&amp;rsquo;s about the political maneuvering of Robert Moses, the NYC Parks Commissioner (among other titles) who shaped NYC, but Robert Caro is an excellent writer (and even better researcher), so the book has a strong narrative arc that pulls you through the story. He somehow turns a vote on a bill into &lt;em&gt;compelling drama&lt;/em&gt;. If you&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in reading this book but are too intimidated to start like I was, then stop whatever you&amp;rsquo;re reading now and start &lt;em&gt;The Power Broker&lt;/em&gt;. You won&amp;rsquo;t regret it. I loved it so much I&amp;rsquo;ve started his 5-part Lyndon B. Johnson biography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="favorite-fiction"&gt;Favorite Fiction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Heartbreaking Work of Staggering Genius&lt;/em&gt; by Dave Eggers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book is autobiographical and based on real events in Dave Eggers&amp;rsquo; life, but he calls it a work of fiction (and it&amp;rsquo;s generally classified that way by libraries). This book is deeply moving and sad, but worthwhile. And that ending&amp;hellip; oof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="favorite-design-product-book"&gt;Favorite Design/Product Book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tied between &lt;em&gt;Beauty&lt;/em&gt; by Sagmeister and Walsh, and &lt;em&gt;The Designer&amp;rsquo;s Dictionary of Type&lt;/em&gt; by Sean Adams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Beauty&lt;/em&gt; made the argument that industrial design and architecture of the 20th century was overtaken by Bauhaus and &amp;ldquo;form follows function,&amp;rdquo; at the expense of beauty. In other words, we valued objects and buildings being functional, and devalued beauty as frivolous &amp;ldquo;ornamentation.&amp;rdquo; This book is an argument against this trend. People&amp;rsquo;s lives and society can be improved by having more beauty in it. As a product designer, I got caught up in &amp;ldquo;form follows function&amp;rdquo; and not valuing beauty, and this book pushed me to re-evaluate that (which is part of the reason I visually updated my site recently).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Designer&amp;rsquo;s Dictionary of Type&lt;/em&gt; gave me a deeper appreciation of typefaces, more so than any previous type book I&amp;rsquo;ve read. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure why, since this book follows a familiar format of grouping type into different families (serif, blackletter, script, etc.) and giving the history of the most famous typefaces in each category. But it may have been the right book at the right time. I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing hand lettering for the past couple of years, which got me to engage deeply with letters and their shapes and curves and forms, which may have magnified all the minor differences between each font that I had previously overlooked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="biggest-disappointments"&gt;Biggest Disappointments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Play Bigger&lt;/em&gt;. This talked about a lot of ideas I have seen batted around for awhile (specifically, being a &amp;ldquo;category defining company&amp;rdquo;), so it didn&amp;rsquo;t feel particularly novel. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s because I&amp;rsquo;m a few years late to it. It also rang hollow because it basically says to create a category for your product, but then pays lip service to the fact that your product &lt;em&gt;actually has to be different enough to be a new category&lt;/em&gt;. It also cites Apple and Facebook as examples throughout the book, but they are such wild outliers of success, and so many factors (many out of their control) contributed to their wild success, that citing them as examples is not particularly helpful or compelling evidence for why their ideas are correct or can be replicated. You know, survivor bias and all that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other disappointment was &lt;em&gt;The Messy Middle&lt;/em&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t disagree with anything in this book, but I also didn&amp;rsquo;t get anything new out of it. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen all these ideas in other books/articles/podcasts. It had a lot of vignettes of ideas about the creative process that weren&amp;rsquo;t particularly deep, and didn&amp;rsquo;t make me see anything in a new way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="full-list"&gt;Full List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sagmeister &amp;amp; Walsh: Beauty&lt;/em&gt; by Stefan Sagmeister and Jessica Walsh (1/1/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The System of the World&lt;/em&gt; by Neal Stephenson (1/6/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The War of Art: Break Through the Blocks and Win Your Inner Creative Battles&lt;/em&gt; by Steven Pressfield (1/8/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thinking with Type: A Critical Guide for Designers, Writers, Editors, and Students&lt;/em&gt; by Ellen Lupton (1/11/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;How To&lt;/em&gt; by Michael Bierut (2/3/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Messy Middle&lt;/em&gt; by Scott Belsky (2/12/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mad Men Carousel&lt;/em&gt; by Matt Zoller Seitz (2/19/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Company of One&lt;/em&gt; by Paul Jarvis (2/24/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Secret Lives of Color&lt;/em&gt; by Kassia St. Clair (3/10/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Designer&amp;rsquo;s Dictionary of Type&lt;/em&gt; by Sean Adams (5/16/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Power Broker&lt;/em&gt; by Robert Caro (6/3/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Making of a Manager&lt;/em&gt; by Julie Zhou (6/17/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Circle&lt;/em&gt; by Dave Eggers (7/6/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bad Blood&lt;/em&gt; by John Carreyrou (7/14/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Working&lt;/em&gt; by Robert Caro (7/24/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hard-boiled Wonderland and the End of the World&lt;/em&gt; by Haruki Murakami (8/25/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Next Level Basic&lt;/em&gt; by Stassi Schroeder (8/26/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Art of Noticing&lt;/em&gt; by Rob Walker (9/6/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Writing&lt;/em&gt; by Stephen King (9/18/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Medium is the Massage&lt;/em&gt; by Marshall McLuhan and Quentin Fiore (9/19/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Design Leadership: How Top Design Leaders Build and Grow Successful Organizations&lt;/em&gt; by Richard Banfield (10/6/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Heartbreaking Work of Staggering Genius&lt;/em&gt; by Dave Eggers (10/10/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Play Bigger&lt;/em&gt; by Christopher Lochhead, Al Ramadan, Dave Peterson, and Kevin Maney (10/23/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Palette Perfect&lt;/em&gt; by Lauren Wager (11/10/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Keep Going&lt;/em&gt; by Austin Kleon (11/11/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Salt Fat Acid Heat&lt;/em&gt; by Samin Nosrat (11/18/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;In Progress&lt;/em&gt; by Jessica Hische (11/21/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Decision Book&lt;/em&gt; by Mikael Krogerus and Roman Tschäppeler (11/24/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ways of Seeing&lt;/em&gt; by John Berger (11/28/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solar Lottery&lt;/em&gt; by Philip K. Dick (12/12/19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A cautionary tale about the importance of designing every screen</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2019/11/23/a-story-about-the-importance-of-designing-every-screen/"/>
    <id>/2019/11/23/a-story-about-the-importance-of-designing-every-screen/</id>
    <published>2019-11-24T00:27:00Z</published>
    <updated>2019-11-24T00:27:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;What does the &amp;lsquo;Archived&amp;rsquo; tab look like?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was walking the engineers through the final designs of some admin screens when they asked me this. The page is just a table of objects, with a tab showing the active ones, and another tab showing archived ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t explicitly designed the &amp;ldquo;Archived&amp;rdquo; tab since it was the same basic design as the accompanying active tab – a table. But I told the engineers I would mock it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected mocking it up to take a few minutes. Boy was I naive! As I mocked it up I discovered a bunch of complexity that I hadn’t anticipated (and the engineers hadn’t anticipated either). What’s the un-archive flow? These objects can be nested inside of each other (like folders), so does un-archiving a parent un-archive all of its descendants? If a child is nested, but the parent is active, how do we display that in the table (on the active tab, children are visually shown underneath and indented from parents, but if the parent isn’t archived the child will be &amp;ldquo;orphaned&amp;rdquo; on the archived tab)? If a parent and its children are archived, can you un-archive just a child? If so, where does it appear in the active hierarchy (it will once again be &amp;ldquo;orphaned&amp;rdquo;)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mocked up these flows and made some product and design decisions to address the above complexity based on what the user would expect in these situations, and what I believe is technically possible based on my understanding of how the feature is being built. I shared it with the engineers and luckily they agreed with my decisions, so we had a happy ending (for now, at least — more unforeseen complexity may pop up while they code it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson here is that you should always &lt;strong&gt;design every screen&lt;/strong&gt;, even if you assume it will look the same as another similar screen. Engineers appreciate you being explicit, and in the worst case (or best case, depending on your perspective), you’ll discover open questions that need to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
