<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Jeff Zych</title>
  <subtitle></subtitle>
  <id>http://jlzych.com/</id>
  <link href="http://jlzych.com/"/>
  <link href="http://jlzych.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2013-10-08T16:47:00Z</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Jeff Zych</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Extend - SASS's Awkward Stepchild</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2013/10/08/extend-sass-s-awkward-stepchild/"/>
    <id>/2013/10/08/extend-sass-s-awkward-stepchild/</id>
    <published>2013-10-08T16:47:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-10-08T16:47:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;SASS has a lot of really powerful features to help you write &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don&amp;#x27;t_repeat_yourself"&gt;DRY&lt;/a&gt; code quickly. One such feature is &lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt;, which I find is overlooked by many developers but can be very useful when used properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;@-what?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a little background on &lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt;. It allows a selector to &lt;em&gt;extend&lt;/em&gt; the styles of another selector, essentially providing a form of sub-classing. &lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt; works by combining selectors into a single comma-separated selector. A simple example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.button&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mh"&gt;#bada55&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;font-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;1em&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.button-small&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;@extend&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;.button&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;font-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;.8em&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which outputs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight css"&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.button&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.button-small&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;#bada55&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;font-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;1em&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.button-small&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;font-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0.8em&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://sass-lang.com/docs/yardoc/file.SASS_REFERENCE.html#extend"&gt;SASS docs&lt;/a&gt; give a fuller explanation of how it works, and its limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why it&amp;rsquo;s great&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt; can cut down duplicate styles and selectors. Modules derived from a base style can all &lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt; the parent, and all the sub-classes will be added to the base selector. Alternative ways to achieve this in SASS include using mixins to output the base styles (which just adds bloat to the stylesheet, since the same set of rules is output multiple places in the final CSS); duplicate the properties in each selector (violates the principle of DRY and is a maintenance nightmare); or manually add each new selector to the base selector (also violates DRY and also is a maintenance nightmare, and the exact problem &lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt; was designed to solve).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Placeholder selectors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Placeholder selectors make &lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt; even sweeter. They are selectors that aren&amp;rsquo;t output unless extended by another selector (also known as &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abstract_type"&gt;abstract classes&lt;/a&gt; in OOP). It doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound like much, but I often run into situations where I have some classes (or elements) that share common styles, but I don&amp;rsquo;t need the base class in the HTML or CSS. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.container-blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.container-red&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;padding&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;3em&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;100%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.container-blue&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="no"&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.container-red&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="no"&gt;red&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each container selector has to be typed out twice &amp;ndash; once for their shared styles, and again for their specific styles. Not a big deal here, but quickly becomes unweildy the more sub-containers you add. Placeholder selectors can help us here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;%container-common-styles&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;padding&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;3em&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;100%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.container-blue&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;@extend&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;%container-common-styles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="no"&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.container-red&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;@extend&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;%container-common-styles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="no"&gt;red&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the common styles are in one place, and each class is in one place. This pays off the more selectors you have extending the placeholder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also feel guilt-free about using unsemantic, descriptive names, since the placeholder itself isn&amp;rsquo;t output in the final CSS. They are purely for yourself and other developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Dangers of @extend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any SASS you write, you need to keep an eye on the final CSS it outputs. If you &lt;code&gt;@extend&lt;/code&gt; a class that&amp;rsquo;s used in many places, the selector will be copied to every instance of that class (even if it&amp;rsquo;s nested in other selectors). This is often unnecessary, and can cause unintended side effects (I ran into a nasty styling bug because of this once).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a &lt;code&gt;.button&lt;/code&gt; class is originally defined in one place, but modified to look slightly different in a dialog. When extending it, you only wanted the original styles, but the new selector is copied into the dialog button as well. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t what you intended, isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary, and bloated your final CSS. Before extending classes, check everywhere they&amp;rsquo;re defined and make sure you want your selector to be duplicated in all of those places. (Arguably, this is bad CSS to begin with [you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t change a button style based on the dialog context in the first place], but in real world CSS it happens).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the depth and breadth of selectors you have nested under the base selector, combined with the number of selectors extending the base, can create some &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; long selectors, not all of which are necessary. Once again, pay attention to the CSS that&amp;rsquo;s being compiled. And once again, this is arguably bad SASS (mind the &lt;a href="http://thesassway.com/beginner/the-inception-rule"&gt;Inception Rule&lt;/a&gt;), but these things happen in legacy codebases with multiple developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extending selectors can save you time and DRY out your code, when used properly. As with most SASS features, it can be abused and create some pretty hairy CSS, but as long as you keep an eye on the final CSS you&amp;rsquo;ll be fine.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Framing your message for maximum impact</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2013/09/30/framing-your-message-for-maximum-impact/"/>
    <id>/2013/09/30/framing-your-message-for-maximum-impact/</id>
    <published>2013-10-01T04:09:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-10-01T04:09:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A common piece of advice in the website optimization space is to test headlines and copy to find the optimal messaging. But there are endless possibilities and it’s not feasible to test them all, so how do you focus your tests on only the content that’s most likely to have an impact? Having a good hypothesis of why a change will be effective is key, and one such theory is &lt;strong&gt;framing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Framing is the simple idea that &lt;strong&gt;different ways of presenting the same information will evoke different emotional responses&lt;/strong&gt;, and thus influence a person’s decision. A simple example is the statement, &amp;ldquo;the odds of survival one month after surgery are 90%&amp;rdquo; is more reassuring than the equivalent statement of, &amp;ldquo;mortality within one month of surgery is 10%.&amp;rdquo; Although these statements present the same information, they bring drastically different associations to mind. With the former it’s easy to envision an outcome of survival (and thus be willing to go through with the surgery), whereas the latter evokes death (and will be less likely to take the perceived risk).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subtleties of framing a message are well known to marketers. For example, &lt;a href="http://www.citycliq.com/"&gt;CityCliq&lt;/a&gt; saw an &lt;a href="http://www.abtests.com/test/284001/landing-for-citycliq"&gt;89% conversion increase&lt;/a&gt; by changing their headline from, &amp;ldquo;Businesses grow faster online!&amp;rdquo; to, &amp;ldquo;Create a webpage for your business.&amp;rdquo; (They have since further optimized their homepage to have a different headline). The original headline is abstract and framed passively, whereas the winning variation is framed in an action-oriented way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea can be used more widely than for just selling products &amp;mdash; any organization that’s trying to spur people to action can make use of it as well. Convincing people to volunteer for a cause, sign a petition, donate money, etc., can all be greatly influenced by the way the message is framed. For example, &lt;a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/7789354"&gt;Banks, et al.&lt;/a&gt;, studied how this phenomenon affects behavior by showing two groups of women videos on breast cancer and mammography in order to convince them to get screened. The first group&amp;rsquo;s video was gain-framed, espousing the benefits of having a mammogram, whereas the second group&amp;rsquo;s video was loss-framed and emphasized the risks of not having one. Only 51.5% of those who saw the gain-framed video got a mammography, compared to 61.2% of the latter group (an 18% increase). The information presented was equivalent, but receiving it in a loss-framed context forced people to imagine the scenario of having breast cancer, which spurred them to action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you know which way to frame your message? There are no one-size-fits-all rules &amp;mdash; it’s still important to test variations. But now instead of arbitrarily changing words (which could go on ad infinitum) you have a narrower and more focused approach to crafting messages. What you want to avoid is testing essentially equivalent phrases that are unlikely to have any significant impact on your goals. For example, the phrases, &amp;ldquo;the odds of survival one month after surgery are 90%&amp;rdquo; and, &amp;ldquo;there is a 90% chance you will be alive a month after surgery&amp;rdquo; contain the same information and are framed equivalently, and thus aren’t likely to change your visitors’ behavior. Instead, &lt;strong&gt;you should think about strikingly different ways you can frame your value proposition&lt;/strong&gt; and test each of them. Try asking yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is this positive or negative (e.g. the odds of survival example)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is this loss-framed or gain-framed (e.g. the mammography study)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is this action-oriented or passive (e.g. the CityCliq create a web page example)?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More generally, what associations are brought to mind? For example, deli meats that advertise &amp;ldquo;95% fat free&amp;rdquo; sounds healthy, whereas &amp;ldquo;Only 5% fat&amp;rdquo; sounds unhealthy. This is tricky to ascertain a priori, but you can read messages to people around you (co-workers, friends, family) and ask what first comes to mind when they hear it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your message may not have a clear answer for all of these, but for the pertinent questions you should &lt;strong&gt;test messages with the opposite framing&lt;/strong&gt;. More likely than not, one of them will resonate better with your audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more on this topic, read chapter 7 of Daniel Kahneman’s book, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Thinking-Fast-Slow-Daniel-Kahneman/dp/0374275637/"&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow.&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Using Gradients In Place of Images</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2013/09/22/using-gradients-in-place-of-images/"/>
    <id>/2013/09/22/using-gradients-in-place-of-images/</id>
    <published>2013-09-23T04:56:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-23T04:56:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently at &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com"&gt;Optimizely&lt;/a&gt;, I needed to create ribbons as part of the design of our &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com/ecommerce-ab-testing"&gt;Summertime Christmas&lt;/a&gt; campaign (see image below). The easy way would have been to throw a repeating background image on some &lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt;s, but then I remembered CSS3 gradients can be used to create some pretty interesting patterns (for example, see &lt;a href="http://lea.verou.me/"&gt;Lea Verou&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://lea.verou.me/css3patterns/"&gt;CSS3 patterns gallery&lt;/a&gt;). Besides being a novel use of gradients, it also makes my markup more semantic (no empty container &lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt;s required), and makes the design more flexible (everything is generated programmatically, and thus easily changeable, unlike images).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Summertime Christmas campaign with ribbon background" src="http://jlzych.com/images/2013-09-22-using-gradients-in-place-of-images/summertime-xmas.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ribbons of Summertime Christmas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Technique&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic technique is to make the color stops end and start at the same place, thus creating hard lines between colors. Then, set the &lt;code&gt;background-size&lt;/code&gt; so the ribbon occupies a specific width instead of spreading across the entire element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the code for the vertical ribbon (vendor-specific properties left out deliberately):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight css"&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;background&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;linear-gradient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nt"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;right&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nf"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nt"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;//&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;starts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;at&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;same&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;spot&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt;
                  &lt;span class="o"&gt;//&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;ends&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;creating&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;hard&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nt"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nf"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nf"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;88&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nt"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;88&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nt"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;92&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nf"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;92&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;background-repeat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;no-repeat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;background-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;80px&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;%;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p data-height="268" data-theme-id="0" data-slug-hash="DhIJp" data-user="jlzych" data-default-tab="result" class='codepen'&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href='http://codepen.io/jlzych/pen/DhIJp'&gt;Vertical ribbon&lt;/a&gt; by Jeff (&lt;a href='http://codepen.io/jlzych'&gt;@jlzych&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a href='http://codepen.io'&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async src="http://codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using percentages for the color stops (instead of hard-coded pixel values) allowed me to adjust the width of the ribbon by changing just one number — the first parameter of the &lt;code&gt;background-size&lt;/code&gt;. (One thing to be careful of is that the ribbon can render imprecisely in certain browsers when the width gets small, so you may need to use pixel values in these situations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add the horizontal ribbon, it&amp;rsquo;s a simple matter of layering multiple &lt;code&gt;background-image&lt;/code&gt;s on top of each other (by providing a comma-separated list of values, the first of which is on top), and switching the vertical and horizontal values of the &lt;code&gt;background-size&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight css"&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.ribbons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;linear-gradient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;right&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="m"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="m"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="m"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;88&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;88&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;92&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="m"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;92&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;linear-gradient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;bottom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="m"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="m"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;12&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="m"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;88&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;88&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;92&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="m"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;92&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="m"&gt;#1964af&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;//&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;darker&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;blue&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;behind&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;ribbons&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-repeat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;no-repeat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;center&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;center&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;80px&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;100&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;80px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cover&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p data-height="268" data-theme-id="0" data-slug-hash="pBwLs" data-user="jlzych" data-default-tab="result" class='codepen'&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href='http://codepen.io/jlzych/pen/pBwLs'&gt;Vertical and horizontal ribbon&lt;/a&gt; by Jeff (&lt;a href='http://codepen.io/jlzych'&gt;@jlzych&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a href='http://codepen.io'&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async src="http://codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Some SCSS to Save Us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve probably noticed there are a lot of repeated values within each &lt;code&gt;linear-gradient&lt;/code&gt;. You also probably noticed that the vertical and horizontal ribbons use the same &lt;code&gt;linear-gradient&lt;/code&gt;, except for the direction they&amp;rsquo;re rendered (the first parameter). As I was developing this, it quickly became cumbersome to fiddle with the ribbon&amp;rsquo;s sizing and color, so I leveraged SCSS to help me out. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to explain everything that&amp;rsquo;s going on here, but am providing this code for anyone who finds it useful (and for my own future reference).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.ribbons&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// Variable declarations
&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mh"&gt;#4783bf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;80px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="m"&gt;8%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;12%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;88%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;92%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-gradient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-blue&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-blue&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-blue&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;transparent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-blue&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$stops&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// Ribbon background stuff
&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$new-blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nd"&gt;background&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nf"&gt;linear-gradient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;right&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-gradient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nf"&gt;linear-gradient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;bottom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-gradient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$new-blue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="k"&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nd"&gt;background-size&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-width&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;100%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;100%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ribbon-width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;cover&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;center&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;center&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;background-repeat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;no-repeat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, so much cleaner and compact! And it puts every value in one place, making it easy to tweak any aspect of the ribbon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;One More Example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recently used this technique on the &lt;a href="http://styleguide.optimizely.com"&gt;Optimizely styleguide&lt;/a&gt; to create the light blue stripe in our navigation, instead of creating a background image or using multiple elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Optimizely styleguide navigation" src="http://jlzych.com/images/2013-09-22-using-gradients-in-place-of-images/styleguide-nav.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Optimizely&amp;rsquo;s styleguide navigation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technique is handy for avoiding image creation, which improves page performance (by avoiding HTTP requests and reducing bandwidth usage), and makes the design easier to modify (no need to fire up Photoshop to make changes!). This example is just scratching the surface of novel ways gradients can be used to draw images in the browser.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Importance of Good Defaults</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2013/09/09/the-importance-of-good-defaults/"/>
    <id>/2013/09/09/the-importance-of-good-defaults/</id>
    <published>2013-09-10T01:32:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-10T01:32:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the simplest and most robust findings from &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Behavioral_economics"&gt;behavioral economics&lt;/a&gt; is that when people are faced with a choice they tend to stick with the default option. This sounds like something that shouldn’t have any effect on people. Common sense leads us to believe we&amp;rsquo;ll always choose whichever option benefits us the most, regardless of the default. Although this intuitively makes sense, numerous studies show that&amp;rsquo;s not the case. For example, most countries have an option for people to donate their organs upon their death. In America, the default choice is to not donate organs, meaning they must specifically check a box on a form (an &amp;ldquo;opt-in&amp;rdquo; system). As a result, the consent rate is only about 28%. In contrast, Belgium’s default option is to donate organs (an &amp;ldquo;opt-out&amp;rdquo; system), in which about 98% of the population consent to donation (&lt;a href="http://www.dangoldstein.com/papers/DefaultsScience.pdf"&gt;read the fully study here [pdf]&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many explanations for this behavior. One reason is that making a choice takes effort (even if it’s only checking a box), whereas sticking with the default is effortless. Another reason is when decisions have unclear costs and benefits that are difficult to evaluate (such as organ donation), defaults can imply the &amp;ldquo;recommended&amp;rdquo; option, thus saving people the time of thinking through the choice themselves. It also sends the signal that this is the option most people choose and is a safe bet (which reinforces the idea of &lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/08/02/everyones-reading-this-increase-conversions-with-social-proof/"&gt;social proof&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Applications to Web Design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applying this insight to web pages is fairly straightforward: when presenting people with a choice, provide a default option. The simplest method is to pre-populate form fields with the most common choice. For example, the checkout form of an ecommerce store whose customers are mainly American should have &amp;ldquo;United States&amp;rdquo; already chosen as the default country. Obviously, there may be customers from other countries, but they would have to select an option were it left blank anyway. This decreases friction when completing a form, decreases errors, and &lt;a href="http://www.nngroup.com/articles/the-power-of-defaults/"&gt;increases usability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous scenario is useful, but unlikely to increase conversions significantly. Defaults really shine when people are faced with a less clear-cut choice. For example, if you have multiple service plans, highlighting one will guide people to that option. Deciding which option to make the default is something you should A/B test, but a good approach is to use existing customer data to preselect the most popular option. For example, if you have multiple pricing tiers, you could highlight the most common one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="No default plan highlighted" src="http://jlzych.com/images/2013-09-09-the-importance-of-good-defaults/no-default.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No recommended plan&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="The most popular plan is highlighted" src="http://jlzych.com/images/2013-09-09-the-importance-of-good-defaults/default.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The most popular &amp;ldquo;Plus&amp;rdquo; plan is highlighted&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another strategy is to select the option you want your potential customers to select (such as the one that earns you the most profit). This will subtly nudge potential customers towards this option. For example, &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com"&gt;Optimizely&lt;/a&gt; ran an experiment recommending their Gold plan and saw a 20% increase in signups to that option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recommending pricing plans is just one way that default options can be applied to web design. Consider experimenting with your forms, account settings, preferences, or anywhere else people face a choice. By providing a default option to fall back on, you&amp;rsquo;re doing a favor for your customers and yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read Eric Johnson and Daniel Goldstein&amp;rsquo;s full study on defaults, titled &lt;a href="http://www.dangoldstein.com/papers/DefaultsScience.pdf"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Do defaults save lives?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (2003).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Automating Semantic Sprites with Compass</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2013/09/01/automating-semantic-sprites-with-compass/"/>
    <id>/2013/09/01/automating-semantic-sprites-with-compass/</id>
    <published>2013-09-02T04:15:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-09-02T04:15:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/08/26/a-more-semantic-approach-to-spriting-images/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;, I explained how to use image sprites semantically. But as with all image spriting, setting each sprite&amp;rsquo;s size and position is a pain. &lt;a href="http://compass-style.org"&gt;Compass&lt;/a&gt; can automate this, but it&amp;rsquo;s designed with the assumption that all your sprites will be background images of elements. Even so, Compass provides a number of under-documented functions that can help automate my technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Refresher&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a quick summary of my &lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/08/26/a-more-semantic-approach-to-spriting-images/"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href="http://css-tricks.com/css-sprites/"&gt;standard way to sprite images&lt;/a&gt; is to set the sprite sheet as the &lt;code&gt;background-image&lt;/code&gt; of an element, and set its &lt;code&gt;background-position&lt;/code&gt; to the coordinates of the image you want to display. But if your image is part of the content, then semantically it should be in the markup as an &lt;code&gt;img&lt;/code&gt; tag. To accomplish this, set the &lt;code&gt;img&lt;/code&gt; tag&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt; to the sprite sheet, and use a container element as a &amp;ldquo;window&amp;rdquo; to let one sprite show through at a time. For the specifics of how to do this, &lt;a href="http://jlzych.com/2013/08/26/a-more-semantic-approach-to-spriting-images/"&gt;read my post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Automate this with Compass&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned, the most difficult part of spriting is setting the image size and position for each sprite. Luckily, Compass can help us, but their &lt;a href="http://compass-style.org/help/tutorials/spriting/"&gt;spriting documentation&lt;/a&gt; is geared towards the standard technique, and thus doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide much help to accomplish my method. But fear not! Compass can still help us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Create the sprite sheet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step to doing any spriting in Compass is to &lt;code&gt;@import&lt;/code&gt; a folder of images. Compass will generate a sprite sheet image, and create a number of variables that we can use to get the size and position of each sprite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;@import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;sprites/*.png&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sprite Dimensions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we need to get the dimensions of each sprite, and set the container element to that size. Compass provides a &lt;code&gt;sprite-dimensions&lt;/code&gt; function, which takes 2 parameters: the sprite map Compass generated, and the name of the sprite (i.e. the filename, sans extension). Then it outputs the &lt;code&gt;width&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;height&lt;/code&gt; of the sprite. If you have no idea what you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to pass as the sprite map parameter, you&amp;rsquo;re not alone. After &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriseppstein/compass/blob/stable/lib/compass/sprite_importer/content.erb#L16"&gt;some digging&lt;/a&gt;, I discovered Compass assigns the sprite map to a variable named &lt;code&gt;$&amp;lt;folder&amp;gt;-sprites&lt;/code&gt;. In this example, that makes the variable the awkwardly named &lt;code&gt;$sprites-sprites&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nd"&gt;sprite-dimensions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprites-sprites&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;my-sprite&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Sprite Position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next step is to set the &lt;code&gt;top&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;left&lt;/code&gt; properties of the image tag. Once again, Compass provides us a helper function: the aptly named &lt;code&gt;sprite-position&lt;/code&gt;. Like &lt;code&gt;sprite-dimensions&lt;/code&gt;, it also takes the sprite map and sprite name as parameters. But unlike &lt;code&gt;sprite-dimensions&lt;/code&gt;, it provides us the &lt;code&gt;left&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;top&lt;/code&gt; properties concatenated in a string, e.g. &amp;ldquo;20px 120px&amp;rdquo;. This seems weird and inconsistent at first, until you realize it&amp;rsquo;s designed to be used as the value of the &lt;code&gt;background-position&lt;/code&gt; property. To help us access each value individually, SASS has a function named &lt;code&gt;nth&lt;/code&gt;, which returns the value at the position you pass it (starting from 1). And don&amp;rsquo;t worry about converting that string to an array &amp;mdash; SASS will automatically convert strings to arrays, splitting the string on spaces. So that gives us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.my-sprite&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;sprite-position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprites-sprites&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;my-sprite&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;left&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;top&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Putting it All Together&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we have all the pieces in place to position each individual sprite, and all we need is the name of each image. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;@import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;sprites/*.png&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.sprite-container&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// or inline-block
&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;overflow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;hidden&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;relative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="k"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.my-sprite&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nd"&gt;sprite-dimensions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprites-sprites&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;my-sprite&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="nt"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;sprite-position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprites-sprites&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;my-sprite&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="nl"&gt;position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;absolute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="nl"&gt;left&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="nl"&gt;top&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// ...etc. for each sprite
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious flaw here is that you need to write code for each sprite in the sprite sheet. Luckily for us, Compass has one more trick up its sleeve to help automate this: the &lt;a href="https://github.com/chriseppstein/compass/blob/stable/lib/compass/sass_extensions/functions/sprites.rb#L14"&gt;&lt;code&gt;sprite_names&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; function. Pass it a sprite map, and it outputs a list of sprite names. Then we can use &lt;code&gt;@each&lt;/code&gt; to loop through the list, and generate the size and position of each. Bringing it all together, our code looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;@import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;quot;sprites/*.png&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprite-names&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;sprite_names&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprites-sprites&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.sprite-container&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// or inline-block
&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;overflow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;hidden&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;relative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="k"&gt;@each&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;sprite&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="err"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;sprite-names&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.sprite-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="k"&gt;@include&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nd"&gt;sprite-dimensions&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprites-sprites&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

      &lt;span class="nt"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;sprite-position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprites-sprites&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;$sprite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nl"&gt;position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;absolute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nl"&gt;left&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="nl"&gt;top&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;nth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// @each
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// .sprite-container
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whew, that was a whirlwind of Compass code. But once you get it all set up, it works quite well. You can add and remove sprites as you please, without needing to update a single line of SCSS. Happy spriting!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A More Semantic Approach to Spriting Images</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="/2013/08/26/a-more-semantic-approach-to-spriting-images/"/>
    <id>/2013/08/26/a-more-semantic-approach-to-spriting-images/</id>
    <published>2013-08-27T04:24:00Z</published>
    <updated>2013-08-27T04:24:00Z</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Zych</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update (9/1/2013): Read my &lt;a href="/2013/09/01/automating-semantic-sprites-with-compass/"&gt;follow up&lt;/a&gt; on how to automate this with Compass.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spriting images is a well-known, well-documented way to speed up page load times. The standard technique is to set a sprite sheet image as the &lt;code&gt;background-image&lt;/code&gt; of an element, and position it so the proper sprite shows through. This works great for icons and other images that aren&amp;rsquo;t part of the actual content, but not so great for images that belong in the page content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Images that are part of the content should be in &lt;code&gt;img&lt;/code&gt; tags. This is correct semantically, good for accessibility, and good for interoperability. With the typical approach to spriting images, you would need empty container elements that have a &lt;code&gt;background-image&lt;/code&gt; property. Those empty elements have no semantic meaning, and are worthless to screenreaders and other crawlers that may access your page. This is the situation I found myself in on &lt;a href="https://www.optimizely.com"&gt;Optimizely&amp;rsquo;s homepage&lt;/a&gt; when I sprited the customer logos and benefits graphics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving this problem is actually fairly simple. First, you&amp;rsquo;ll need markup similar to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight html"&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;class=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;sprite-container sprite-track&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;src=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;sprites.png&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;alt=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Graphic of tracking elements on a web page&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://codepen.io/jlzych/pen/ExLzG"&gt;View the Codepen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;.sprite-container&lt;/code&gt; element acts as a window that only lets one sprite show through. It has the same width and height as the sprite, and has &lt;code&gt;overflow: hidden&lt;/code&gt; to prevent the other sprites from showing through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the image needs to be positioned so the sprite we want shown is at the top left corner of the window, which is accomplished by setting &lt;code&gt;position: absolute&lt;/code&gt; and the &lt;code&gt;top&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;left&lt;/code&gt; properties correctly. SCSS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight scss"&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.sprite-container&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;display&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;inline-block&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// or block
&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;height&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;275px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;          &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// size of the image we want to show
&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;width&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;400px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;overflow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;hidden&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;       &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// prevent the other sprites from showing
&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="nl"&gt;position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;relative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// so the image can be positioned absolutely
&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="nt"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nl"&gt;position&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;absolute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="k"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nc"&gt;.sprite-track&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;img&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nl"&gt;left&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nl"&gt;top&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="m"&gt;-210px&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

  &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// other sprites
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Codepen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p data-height="268" data-theme-id="0" data-slug-hash="ExLzG" data-user="jlzych" data-default-tab="result" class='codepen'&gt;See the Pen &lt;a href='http://codepen.io/jlzych/pen/ExLzG'&gt;ExLzG&lt;/a&gt; by Jeff (&lt;a href='http://codepen.io/jlzych'&gt;@jlzych&lt;/a&gt;) on &lt;a href='http://codepen.io'&gt;CodePen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script async src="http://codepen.io/assets/embed/ei.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generating this CSS can be a pain, but I will discuss how to accomplish this with Compass in my &lt;a href="/2013/09/01/automating-semantic-sprites-with-compass/"&gt;next blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This method lets us use sprites in &lt;code&gt;img&lt;/code&gt; tags, which is more semantic than empty &lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt;s or &lt;code&gt;span&lt;/code&gt;s (depending on the use case). However, it has a couple of drawbacks. First, it requires a container element around your image. This could add unneccessary bloat to your markup (in my case the image already had a parent element). Second, and greatest of all, the image &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt; attribute now references an entire sprite sheet, when technically it should only reference the actual image that it&amp;rsquo;s showing. Screenreaders won&amp;rsquo;t care at all, but some services may use this image for other purposes. For example, Facebook grabs a representative image of your page when a link is shared, and it could grab a sprite sheet instead of the actual image. That&amp;rsquo;s no good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately it&amp;rsquo;s a tradeoff between having a container element and actual &lt;code&gt;img&lt;/code&gt; tag in your markup versus an empty element whose background image is a sprite. Overall, I think the pros (semantic HTML; better accessibility) outweigh the cons (container element; &lt;code&gt;src&lt;/code&gt; attribute is a sprite sheet). If you want to use sprites with actual &lt;code&gt;img&lt;/code&gt; tags, this is a solid technique. If anyone has any thoughts on how to overcome the drawbacks, hit me up &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/jlzych"&gt;@jlzych&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update (9/1/2013): Read my &lt;a href="/2013/09/01/automating-semantic-sprites-with-compass/"&gt;follow up&lt;/a&gt; on how to automate this with Compass.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
